♪Don’t be afraid of long journeys♪
♪不要害怕长途旅行♪
♪Love will comfort your thoughts♪
♪爱会安慰你的思念♪
♪All wounds will scab♪
♪所有的伤口都会结痂♪
♪Become the flower of time♪
♪化作时光之花♪
♪Someone will wipe it off for you♪
♪会有人帮你擦掉的♪
♪Don’t feel alone and keep going♪
♪不要感到孤独，继续前进♪
♪Share your story with time♪
♪与时间分享你的故事♪
♪It will respond with a soft beam♪
♪它会 发出柔和的光束回应♪
♪Hope you can find her in the crowd♪
♪希望你能在人群中找到她♪
♪Be content with a simple life♪
♪满足于简单的生活♪
♪Although life is full of regrets♪
♪虽然人生充满遗憾♪
♪May you always remain enthusiastic♪
♪愿你永远保持热情♪
♪Suitable for every winter and summer♪
♪适合每个冬天和夏天♪
[Love is the panacea] [Episode 1]
[爱是灵丹妙药] [第1集]
[The play is a major literary and artistic support project]
【该剧为重大 文艺扶持工程】
[In Sichuan Province in 2022]
【2022年在四川省】
[Adapted from the Ningmeng language novel "The Healer"]
【改编 自凝梦语言小说《治愈者》】
(Day 478 of Lakaya Medical Assistance,)
（拉卡亚医疗救助第478天，）
(I just flew to a nearby city)
（我刚刚飞往邻近城市）
(Guidance on resection of giant meningiomas)
（指导 巨大脑膜瘤的切除手术）
(for patients with heart failure)
（对于患有心力衰竭的患者）
(Then rush back to Lakaya)
（然后赶回拉卡亚）
(Another major surgery awaits me.)
（另一场重大手术 正在等着我。）
(Our mission is twofold:)
（我们的使命是双重的：）
(First, save more lives)
（第一，拯救更多生命）
(The local medical conditions are poor ;)
（当地医疗条件恶劣 ；）
(2. Teach them skills)
（二、教他们技能）
(So ​​when we leave this land,)
（这样当我们离开这片土地时，）
(local doctor)
（当地医生）
(still available)
（仍然可以提供）
(The best treatment for the patient.)
（对患者最好的治疗。）
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
[Lakaya International Airport]
[拉卡亚国际机场]
Have the transferred patients arrived?
转运的病人到了吗？
Yes.
是的。
Patient injured by falling object
患者因坠落物体受伤
With skull fracture and enophthalmos.
伴有颅骨骨折和眼球内陷。
There is obvious runny nose now.
现在有明显的鼻涕。
Due to the limited conditions of local hospitals,
由于 当地医院条件有限，
We only briefly bandaged the open wounds.
我们只 对开放性伤口做了简单的包扎。
The patient is currently in a mild coma.
目前患者处于 轻度昏迷状态。
What is the GCS score?
GCS 分数是多少？
six.
六。
I think this is
我想这是
Comminuted skull base fracture accompanied by cerebrospinal fluid leakage.
颅底粉碎性骨折 并伴有脑脊液漏。
Send me your CT scan now
立即将 CT 扫描发送给我
and be ready for surgery within an hour .
并在一小时内做好手术准备 。
I upgraded my seat to first class
我把座位升级到头等舱
That way I can come out early to save time.
这样我就可以早点出来 以节省时间。
Tell the driver to pick me up
告诉司机来接我
Arrive at Gate 3 in five minutes.
五分钟后到达三号门。
[Lakaya]
[拉卡亚]
The following are shipping charges.
以下是托运费用。
You can pick up your order.
您可以提货。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Hello.
你好。
[Kweichow Moutai Co., Ltd.] moved these two boxes to my car.
[贵州茅台股份有限公司] 把这两箱搬到我的车上。
One dollar per box.
每箱一美元。
beautiful.
美好的。
[My group will be released soon. 】
【我的小组即将出炉。】
The customer is coming!
客户来了！
boss,
老板，
Car Encountered a traffic jam on the way to the airport.
汽车 在去机场的路上遇到交通堵塞。
Traffic in Lakaya is terrible.
拉卡亚的交通非常糟糕。
Time saved by upgrading may be wasted.
升级节省的时间 可能会被浪费。
Can you wait a moment?
你能再等一下吗？
No, I will find a way.
不，我会想办法的。
Hello.
你好。
Everyone, come with me.
大家跟我来吧。
What are the specialties of Lakaya?
拉卡亚有什么特产？
Here we can see...
在这里，我们可以看到...
(Does a stroller still need to be used at such a small airport?)
（这么小的机场还要推车吗？）
Welcome to Lakaya.
欢迎来到拉卡亚。
What's this?
这是什么？
here.
这里。
Do you need Maotai?
你们需要茅台吗？
I guarantee authenticity.
我保证真实性。
Here, separate the leaflets.
在这里，把传单分开。
Buying Moutai in Lacaya,
Buying Moutai in Lacaya,
are you kidding me?
你在跟我开玩笑吗？
that's right.
这是正确的。
Sir, you have no idea how it works.
先生，你不知道它是如何运作的。
this will be a huge loss
这将是一个巨大的损失
If you haven't bought a bottle of Moutai in Lakaya.
如果你没有 在拉卡亚买一瓶茅台酒。
The price per bottle is $100.
每瓶价格为 100 美元。
How about that?
那个怎么样？
You can't buy half a bottle at this price in China.
在中国这个价格你买不到半瓶。
Very cheap. Are they fake?
很便宜。它们是假的吗？
correct. How can I trust you?
正确的。我要怎么相信你？
Exporting Moutai to Lakaya requires paying taxes.
出口茅台酒到拉卡亚 需要缴税，
Each bottle is sold for only 400 to 500 yuan.
每瓶售价仅400至500元。
Miss sister, your profits are too big!
小姐姐， 你的利润太大了！
hurry up,
快点，
This is just a small business.
这只是一个小企业。
I still have to pay customs duties
我还得付关税
Space, rent, labor, etc.
空间、租金、劳动力等
After all, I really can’t make that much.
毕竟， 我真的赚不了那么多。
Still unreliable.
还是不靠谱。
What if they are fake?
如果它们是假的怎么办？
If we drink fake wine...
如果我们喝假酒...
It is indeed too cheap.
确实是太便宜了。
Your body won't accept it.
你的身体不会接受它。
It doesn't matter. You came here to travel,
没关系。你来这里是为了旅行，
So I won't force you to buy anything.
所以我不会强迫你买任何东西。
General Kouyate has ordered wine for me.
库亚特将军已经给我订了酒。
He will serve this dish at a family dinner tomorrow.
他将在明天的家庭宴会上提供这道菜。
wait!
等待！
Moutai in Lacaya
Moutai in Lacaya
It is indeed much cheaper than China.
确实比中国便宜很多。
It’s not very expensive and you can afford it yourself.
不是很贵， 自己也能喝得起。
I will own one.
我会拥有一个。
All right!
好吧！
Really?
真的吗？
Yes!
是的！
All right!
好吧！
Thank you!
谢谢你！
Wait for your turn!
等待轮到你了！
be patient!
要有耐心！
Comminuted fracture of the anterior skull base.
前颅底粉碎性骨折。
We have to remove bone fragments
我们必须去除骨头碎片
Now embedded in the brain and compressing the optic nerve.
现在嵌入大脑 并压迫视神经。
How is the patient?
病人怎么样？
The patient just had an epileptic seizure.
患者刚刚 癫痫发作，
Lasts more than five minutes.
持续五分钟以上。
We give barbiturates for symptomatic treatment.
我们给予巴比妥 进行对症治疗。
GCS has been reduced to 5 points.
GCS 已降至 5 分。
Moderate coma. The left pupil is dilated.
中度昏迷。 左侧瞳孔放大。
Continuously monitor the patient's vital signs.
持续监测 患者的生命体征。
If GCS loses another point,
如果GCS再丢一分，
Just do it immediately without asking me.
不用问我就立即操作。
But the boss,
但是老板，
I...
我...
There is no "but".
没有“但是”。
Fang Mingfan,
Fang Mingfan,
Cerebral herniation won't wait until you 're ready.
脑疝不会等你 准备好。
(Isn’t this the rich man who pulled the cart just now?)
（这不是刚才拉车的有钱人吗？）
I need to hang up now.
我现在需要挂断电话。
My Chinese compatriots,
我的中国同胞们，
where are you going?
你要去哪里？
I can give you a ride.
我可以载你一程。
unnecessary.
不需要。
I'm going to take a taxi.
我要坐出租车。
taxi?
出租车？
Then you need to be prepared.
那你需要做好准备。
Traffic conditions from the airport to main roads
从机场到主干道的交通情况
Going downtown can make you feel depressed.
去市中心会让你感到沮丧。
Take my ride.
搭我的车吧。
I promise it only takes 50 minutes
我保证 只需要50分钟
Get anywhere in the city center.
到达市中心的任何地方。
Fifty minutes?
五十分钟？
are you sure?
你确定吗？
Are you in a hurry?
你很着急吗？
how about this?
这个怎么样？
Because we are all Chinese,
因为我们都是中国人，
I'll charge you $100, no more, no less.
我收你100美元， 不多也不少。
Hundred dollars?
一百美元？
Time is gold.
时间就是金。
I'll pay you $100 if I'm overtime.
如果我超时的话我付给你100美元。
Where is your car?
你的汽车在哪儿？
Deposit first.
先存款。
There are 100 of them here. let's go.
这里有 100 个。我们走吧。
Quite generous! follow me.
相当慷慨！跟我来。
We've been walking for eight minutes.
我们已经走了八分钟了。
Where is your car?
你的车到底在哪里？
I'm really anxious.
我真的很着急。
about there.
差不多了。
Convertible with leather seats .
配有真皮座椅的敞篷车 。
The owner will take you there himself.
店主亲自带你去。
This bike?
这辆自行车？
Where do I sit?
我坐在哪里？
Right here.
就在这儿。
How about luggage?
行李怎么样？
this is very simple,
这很简单，
here.
这里。
I drove very smoothly. completely fine.
我开车非常平稳。 完全没问题。
rest assured.
放心。
are you serious?
你是认真的？
As a doctor,
作为一名医生，
Facing disease but unable to do anything
面对疾病却无能为力
In fact, it is the greatest pain.
其实是最大的痛苦。
one,
一，
If you think my bike is lame
如果你觉得我的自行车很蹩脚
You should take a taxi.
你应该乘坐出租车。
I can give it back to you.
我可以还给你。
Let's go now.
现在就出发吧。
Ten minutes passed.
十分钟过去了。
You have forty left.
你还剩四十个。
hurry up.
赶快。
so,
所以，
where to?
去哪儿？
Friendship Hospital.
友谊医院。
What are you looking at me for?
你看着我干什么？
Keep your eyes on the road!
眼睛盯着路！
Can you go faster?
你能再快一点吗？
hold onto!
紧紧抓住！
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
Are you blind?
你是瞎子吗？
Traffic jam? hurry up.
交通阻塞？快点。
It looked like a car accident.
看起来像是一场车祸。
Is there any other way we could go?
我们还能走其他路吗？
Sit tight!
稳坐！
You need to pay extra for speeding.
您需要为超速支付额外费用。
I told you to drive faster, not to fly!
我叫你开快点，不是坐飞机！
I don't want to die because of you!
我不想因为你而死！
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
Take it easy!
慢慢来！
If the general's wine is spilled
如果将军的酒洒了
us...
我们...
wait...
等待...
What should we do now?
现在怎么办？
We got here ten minutes early.
我们提前十分钟到达这里。
Do you have to pay extra for speeding?
超速还要加钱吧？
No.
不。
Fifty is already twice the price.
五十已经是价格的两倍了。
I should give you 50 back.
我应该还给你50。
It doesn't matter.
没关系。
[Gu Yunzheng]
[Gu Yunzheng]
boss,
老板，
I should leave this to you.
我应该把这个交给你。
vital signs?
生命体征？
vital signs.
生命体征。
Heart rate 65BPM,
心率65BPM，
High pressure 120mmHg,
高压120mmHg，
Blood oxygen saturation is 92%,
血氧饱和度92%，
Vital signs are stable.
生命体征稳定。
PhD. catch,
博士。抓住，
The surgery was very timely.
手术非常及时。
Hello, Jiang.
Hello, Jiang.
next month. I'll be back next month.
下个月。我下个月回来。
Do you think I will believe you?
你以为我会相信你吗？
Su Wei'an,
Su Wei'an,
You say that every month.
你每个月都这么说。
What excuse will you give me next month?
下个月你会给我什么样的借口？
Traffic jam?
交通阻塞？
stomach ache?
腹痛？
Have you slept with it?
你睡过吗？
According to you, the airline has had two strikes.
据你介绍， 该航空公司已经发生过两次罢工。
I promise I'll be back next month.
我保证下个月我会回来。
OK?
好的？
enough.
足够的。
Come pick me up at the airport.
来机场接我吧。
AIRPORT?
飞机场？
What airport?
什么机场？
Lakaya Airport.
拉卡亚机场。
Su Wei'an,
Su Wei'an,
You are so bold.
你真大胆。
i just found out
我刚刚发现
You haven't studied in Paris for three years
你已经三年没有在巴黎读书了
But in Lakaya!
但在拉卡亚！
How dare you hide this from me and Lan for three years!
你居然敢瞒着 我和兰三年！
Just waiting for you!
就等你了！
You'll have to explain it to me when we meet .
我们见面的时候你得给我解释一下 。
wait...
等待...
You didn't tell Lan that I was in Lakaya, right?
你没有告诉兰 我在拉卡亚吧？
Don't you want me to tell your mother?
你不想让我告诉你妈妈吗？
Then come pick me up here.
然后到这里来接我。
But I'm delivering wine
但我是送酒的
Go to the General's Mansion.
到将军府。
You have to wait for over an hour.
你得等一个多小时。
Don't you understand French?
你不懂法语吗？
You can take a shuttle bus.
您可以乘坐接驳巴士。
Hello?
你好？
Wei 'an?
Wei 'an?
River,
江，
I will send you the address.
我会把地址发给你。
be safe.
注意安全。
[East of Longjiang intersection]
【龙江路口以东】
(Your father Su Jianguo passed away on the way to the hospital.)
（你的父亲苏建国 在去医院的路上去世了。）
(He was found to bear full responsibility for the accident.)
（经认定，他 对此次事故负有全部责任。）
Hey, don't touch him!
喂，别动他！
Put him down!
把他放下来！
Are you a doctor?
你是医生吗？
doctor! Lord, he will be saved.
医生！主啊，他一定会得救的。
(Unilateral pupil dilation,)
（单侧瞳孔放大，）
(Difficulty breathing.)
（呼吸困难。）
(Oh no.)
（不好了。）
(Possibly traumatic intracranial hemorrhage.)
（可能是 外伤性颅内出血。）
(High intracranial pressure is very likely to cause brain herniation.)
（颅内压高 ，极有可能引起脑疝。）
Where is the nearest hospital?
最近的医院在哪里？
city ​​center. Still an hour and a half away.
市中心。还有一个半小时的路程。
I can drive him there.
我可以开车送他去那里。
An hour and a half...
一个半小时...
Where is she going?
她去哪？
He might die. what to do?
他可能会死。该怎么办？
The patient has ventricular fibrillation.
患者患有 心室颤动。
Doctor Gu, the patient suffers from
顾医生，患者患有 室颤。
Defibrillator.
除颤器。
Defibrillator!
除颤器！
move.
移动。
Give 1 mg of epinephrine as an intravenous bolus.
静脉推注 1 mg 肾上腺素。
what is she doing?
她在做什么？
Two hundred and fifty joules.
两百五十焦耳。
finished charging.
充电完成。
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
Don't do that!
不要那样做！
You will kill him!
你会杀了他！
stop. I want to save him!
停下来。我要救他！
Two hundred and fifty joules. try again.
两百五十焦耳。再试一次。
She is not a doctor.
她不是医生。
She is the devil!
她就是恶魔！
Call the police!
打电话叫警察！
She was going to murder him!
她这是要谋杀他！
I'll call the police.
我会叫警察。
Don't let her get away.
别让她逃走。
Three hundred joules.
三百焦耳。
The patient returns to sinus rhythm,
患者恢复窦性心律，
Heart rate is 65 BPM,
心率为 65 BPM，
Oxygen saturation is 92%.
氧饱和度为92%。
Continue the surgery.
继续手术。
Yes.
是的。
Send him to the hospital.
送他去医院。
Brain reconstruction completed.
颅脑重建完成。
Fang Mingfan, the rest will be left to you.
方明凡， 剩下的就交给你了。
rest assured.
放心。
My husband returned to his hometown.
我丈夫回到了他的家乡。
I helped him drive his car here.
我帮他开着他的车来这里。
What...
什么...
Where is my motorcycle?
我的摩托车在哪里？
excuse me,
打扰一下，
Where are my motorcycle and wine?
我的摩托车和酒呢？
have no idea.
不知道。
We didn't see that.
我们没有看到。
Here she is.
她在这里。
let's go.
我们走吧。
My motorcycle and wine were gone.
我的摩托车和酒都不见了。
Miss,
女士，
You are suspected of murder.
你涉嫌谋杀。
What?
什么？
you misunderstood.
你误会了。
boss,
老板，
You have worked hard.
你辛苦了。
This is my treasure
这是我的珍藏
Dendrobium officinale in 1982.
1982年的铁皮石斛。
I specially brought it from home.
我特意从家里带过来的。
It is good for the stomach and produces liquid,
它有益于胃 并产生液体，
Nourishes yin and clears away heat.
滋阴清热。
Please try it.
请尝尝。
Fang Mingfan.
Fang Mingfan.
boss,
老板，
Please give me some more time.
请再给我一些时间。
I know.
我知道。
Next time I will definitely...
下次我一定会...
Escape is not the answer.
逃避并不是答案。
Will you be my first assistant for life?
你愿意做我 一辈子的第一助理吗？
The emergency room needs you.
急诊室需要你。
The smell of alcohol is too strong.
酒精味太浓了。
Do you still dare to drive after drinking?
酒后你还敢开车吗？
Send his blood sample to a medical laboratory.
将他的血样送到 医学实验室。
Send him to the operating room now.
现在就送他去手术室。
OK
好的。
I am innocent!
我是无辜的！
[Police] I'm saving him, not killing him!
[警察] 我是在救他，而不是杀他！
I am innocent!
我是无辜的！
Policemen!
警察们！
shut up!
住口！
I am innocent! Policemen!
我是无辜的！警察们！
shut up! You are too loud!
住口！你太大声了！
The person located it by hand without taking a CT scan.
此人在没有进行 CT 扫描的情况下用手定位了它。
Lakaya actually has such an expert neurosurgeon.
拉卡亚居然有 这样一位专家般的神经外科医生。
Not really an expert.
并不是真正的专家。
Isn't the location of this hole precise enough?
这个洞开的位置还不够 精确吗？
The left rear part of the head was the direct point of impact.
头部的左后部 是直接撞击点。
The impact resulted in injury to the right frontal area.
撞击导致 右额叶区域受伤。
Intracranial blood vessel rupture leading to massive bleeding.
颅内血管破裂 导致大出血。
The rescuer must have realized
施救者一定已经意识到
intracranial hypertension
颅内压过高
In order to allow patients to arrive at the hospital smoothly,
为了让病人 能够顺利到达医院，
So he performed emergency treatment.
于是他进行了紧急救治。
He does it very steadily and precisely.
他做得非常稳定和精确。
Don't you think rescuers are experts?
你还不认为 救援者是专家吗？
Thanks to this hole,
多亏了这个洞，
Reduce intracranial pressure promptly
及时降低颅内压
Give us more time.
给我们更多的时间。
Bone fragments were shattered.
骨头碎片都碎了。
He's so unfamiliar with his craftsmanship, yet he still dares to open his head.
手艺这么生疏， 还敢开颅，
He is probably an impulsive quack with limited abilities.
很可能是一个 能力有限、冲动的庸医。
As the saying goes: a lion's heart, an eagle's eye, a woman's hand.
俗话说：狮心、 鹰眼、女人之手。
This quack
这个庸医
At least
至少有
The first two qualities of a good surgeon.
优秀外科医生的前两个品质。
I want to meet this person.
我想见见这个人。
Very interesting indeed.
确实很有趣。
Sir,
长官，
I was literally saving him.
我真的是在救他。
If you don't believe me, you can call a neurosurgeon.
如果你不相信我，你可以打电话给神经外科医生。
All right.
好吧。
I have notified the FBI to investigate this matter.
我已通知FBI调查此事。
When can I leave?
我什么时候可以离开？
Be patient, ma'am.
要有耐心，女士。
The evidence and testimony against you is overwhelming.
对你不利的证据和证词 都是铁证如山。
You'd better pray that the victim makes it through this.
你最好 祈祷受害者能渡过难关。
The district court will hear the case in three months,
地方法院 将在三个月后审理此案，
You can then apply for bail.
届时您可以申请保释。
Three months?
三个月？
Madam, you'd better learn to adapt to this place.
女士，你最好学会 适应这个地方。
(I would miss a lot of money-making opportunities.)
（我会错过很多 赚钱的机会。）
(If I don’t send Maotai,)
（如果我不送茅台的话，）
(The general will hunt me down.)
（将军会追杀我的。）
official!
官！
Which hospital was he sent to?
他被送到哪家医院了？
Friendship Hospital.
友谊医院。
official!
官！
can you lend me a phone
你能借我一部电话吗
Call up?
打电话？
Aren't hundred dollar bills enough?
百元大钞 还不够吗？
How greedy.
多么贪心啊。
Wait a moment.
等一下。
【Lakaya China Trading Company】
【拉卡亚中国贸易公司】
What kind of life does Su Weian live here?
苏薇安在这里过着怎样的生活？
Hello, Wei An.
你好，维安。
I'm at your doorstep
我就在你家门口
Are you sure the address you gave me is correct?
你确定 你给我的地址是正确的吗？
Jiang, listen,
Jiang, listen,
I am suspected of murder.
我涉嫌谋杀。
I'm at the police station now.
我现在在警察局。
murder?
谋杀？
Go to the Neurosurgery Department of Friendship Hospital immediately
立即前往友谊医院神经外科
Look for patients sent there today.
寻找今天送到那里的病人。
He had a car accident due to drunk driving
他因酒后驾车出了车祸
And drilled a whole thing into his head.
并在他的脑袋里钻了一个整体。
regardless,
无论，
You have to find his surgeon.
你必须找到他的外科医生
and took the surgeon to the Eastern District Police Station.
并将外科医生 带到东区警署。
Only a doctor can prove that I did not kill the patient.
只有医生才能证明 我没有杀死病人。
time up.
时间到。
remember…
记住…
Neurosurgery, Friendship Hospital.
友谊医院神经外科。
Hello?
你好？
my God.
我的上帝。
(Neurosurgery, Friendship Hospital)
（友谊医院神经外科）
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
[recruitment]
[招聘]
Hello!
你好！
Are you here to apply for a job as an interpreter?
您是来 申请口译员工作的吗？
No.
不。
Excuse me
请问
If there are emergency patients today
如果今天有急诊病人
who was sent here
谁被派到这里
A hole drilled in your head?
头上钻了一个洞？
You mean the one in the car accident?
你是说车祸中的那个吗？
Yes!
是的！
What is your relationship with him?
你和他是什么关系？
I need to find his surgeon.
我需要找到他的外科医生。
His surgeon was Dr. Gu.
他的主刀医生是顾医生。
What do you need him to do?
你需要他做什么？
I desperately needed to see him!
我非常迫切地需要见他！
This is related to a person's life!
这关系到一个人的一生！
Can you help me find him?
你能帮我找到他吗？
clam down.
冷静下来。
You can go and sit for a while.
你可以去坐一会儿。
I'll inform him now.
我现在就通知他。
Thank you! Please hurry up!
谢谢你！请快点！
excuse me.
打扰一下。
terribly sorry.
非常抱歉。
It doesn't matter.
没关系。
Are you Chinese?
你是中国人吗？
[Neurosurgery] Have you been sick or visited anyone?
[神经外科] 您是否生病或探访过任何人吗？
Do you know Dr. Gu from neurosurgery?
您认识 神经外科的顾医生吗？
I needed him to save a life.
我需要他来拯救一条生命。
save life?
拯救生命？
are you uncomfortable?
你不舒服吗？
I am also in this department.
我也是这个部门的。
not me.
不是我。
I need to see a surgeon
我需要去看外科医生
He drilled a hole in the man's head.
他 在这名男子的头上钻了一个洞。
I had to see him and only him.
我必须见他，而且只能见他。
Same thing with talking to me.
跟我说话也是一样。
I was also involved in that emergency operation.
我也参与了那次紧急行动。
No, my friend said
不，我朋友说
I had to find a surgeon.
我必须找到外科医生。
Are you a surgeon?
你是外科医生吗？
Dr. Gu is very busy.
顾医生很忙。
anything that has nothing to do with the patient
任何与患者无关的事情
Will be handled by me.
将由我处理。
Who needs to see me?
谁需要见我？
Me, doctor.
我，医生。
Please follow me to the East District Police Station.
请随我 到东区派出所。
My friend was arrested by the police
我的朋友被警察逮捕了
when she gives first aid to someone
当她 对某人进行急救时
Charge her with murder.
指控她谋杀。
You are that patient's surgeon,
你是那个病人的外科医生，
So you need to come with me and prove her innocence.
所以你需要跟我一起去 证明她的清白。
Fang Mingfan,
Fang Mingfan,
Hear her out.
听她说完。
If you need,
如果有需要的话，
Give her a written explanation of the situation.
给她书面解释 情况。
OK
好的。
No, Dr. Gu.
不，顾博士。
It is the sacred duty of doctors to save lives and heal the wounded.
救死扶伤是医生的神圣职责。
How can you stand by and watch when lives are at stake?
当生命危在旦夕时，你怎么能袖手旁观呢？
So please don't waste my time while I save lives.
所以，当我拯救生命时，请不要浪费我的时间。
Investigate and collect evidence to learn the truth
调查和收集证据 以了解真相
It's the police's job.
是警察的职责。
My friend will not be falsely accused
我的朋友不会被 错误地指控
If the police here are doing their job.
如果这里的警察 正在履行他们的职责。
you are the only one who knows
你是唯一知道的人
Did my friend hurt or save that person?
我的朋友是否伤害或拯救了那个人
Drill a hole in his head.
在他的头上钻一个洞。
Did your friend get a piercing?
你朋友打孔了吗？
Yes.
是的。
Wait a moment.
等一下。
Let me organize the work at hand
让我安排一下手头的工作
I'll go with you.
我会和你一起去。
But, boss,
但是，老板，
You never interfere in other people's affairs.
你从不插手 别人的事。
Why...
为什么...
Fang Mingfan,
Fang Mingfan,
Where is the blood test report I asked you to get?
我让你拿的验血报告在哪里？
Give me that.
把那个给我。
Wei 'an!
Wei 'an!
River!
江！
Oh my god. How are you?
我的天哪。你还好吗？
I am fine.
我很好。
I am anxious!
我很担心！
Where is the doctor I asked you to find?
我让你找的医生在哪里？
over there.
在那边。
I didn't even waste a minute.
我什至没有浪费一分钟。
He is a very handsome Chinese doctor.
他是一位非常英俊的中国医生。
PhD. Gu.
博士。顾。
official.
官。
Your testimony and blood test results have been received.
您的证词和验血结果 已收到。
You're ready to go.
你已准备好出发。
That gentleman,
那位先生，
Is he okay now?
他现在还好吗？
you are wrong.
你错了。
She is not a gentleman.
她不是一个绅士。
It's that crazy woman over there.
就是那边那个疯女人。
It's you!
是你！
Dr. Gu, the world is really small.
顾博士，世界真小。
Thank you for vouching for me.
谢谢你为我作证。
You know each other!
你们彼此认识！
destiny.
命运。
Are you a doctor?
你是医生吗？
She is a medical student studying
她是一名医学生，正在攻读
Studied at Huaren Medical University for eight years and obtained a doctorate. Cool, right?
在华仁医科大学学习八年 并获得博士学位。很酷，对吧？
Are you a doctoral student at Huaren?
你是华仁的博士生吗？
Yes.
是的。
But why are you working as an unlicensed taxi driver here?
但你为什么 在这里当无证出租车司机呢？
What year did you go to school?
你是哪一年上的学校？
How long has it been since you graduated?
你毕业多久了？
I didn't graduate.
我没有毕业。
I dropped out of school.
我退学了。
What? Why?
什么？为什么？
Then you have no clinical experience
那你就没有临床经验
and did not receive
并且没有收到
Provide remote professional guidance in first aid earlier.
更早提供急救时的远程专业指导。
I obtained my medical license.
我获得了 执业医师证书。
I have specialized training in neurosurgery.
我接受过 神经外科方面的专门培训。
That means no experience.
那就意味着没有经验。
Aren't you afraid of making mistakes?
就不怕 出错吗
In your previous actions,
在你之前的行动中，
Caused the patient to die on the spot?
导致病人当场死亡？
If that's the case,
如果真是这样的话，
How will you take responsibility?
你会如何承担责任？
He's still alive, isn't he?
他还活着，不是吗？
You're just lucky.
你只是幸运。
No wonder you dropped out of school.
难怪你退学了。
I think you have no respect
我看你没有尊重
For medicine or human life.
为了医学或人类生命。
Don't worry!
不用担心！
If he dies, I will compensate him with my life.
如果他死了， 我就用我的命补偿他。
Isn’t your life life?
你的人生不是人生吗？
What is human life for?
人类的生命到底是做什么的
What does it mean to you?
对你来说意味着什么？
Is this the case with Huaren Medical University?
华仁医科大学是这样吗
Teach you to be responsible
教你负责任
For human life?
为了人类的生命？
Just sign your name and you're good to go.
签上名字就可以走了。
Are you that Gu Yunzheng from Huaren?
Are you that Gu Yunzheng from Huaren?
Thanks.
谢谢。
Isn’t Gu Yunzheng your teacher...
顾云铮不是你老师吗……
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
What happened to that man?
那个男人怎么了？
Did he pass out?
他昏过去了吗？
He had a seizure.
他癫痫发作。
He is lucky to have young Dr. Su here.
他很幸运 ，有年轻的苏医生在这里。
He is now taken to hospital.
他现在被送往医院。
PhD. yes?
博士。是？
This is not accurate.
这不准确。
She is a student at Huaren Medical University.
她是华仁医科大学的学生。
She forgot to bring her book.
她忘记带书了。
This was the last subject for her final exam.
这是她期末考试的最后一个科目。
[Sabiston Surgery Textbook]
[萨比斯顿外科教科书]
【We serve patients first and learn from the process,】
【我们首先为患者服务 ，并从过程中学习，】
[Not serving patients is just for learning. ——Academician Wang Zhongcheng]
【不为病人服务只是为了学习。 ——王忠成院士】
[Clinical Medicine Class 2012 Su Weian]
【2012级临床医学班 苏伟安】
Practicing medicine without a license,
无证行医，
Pay a $1,000 fine and you're good to go.
缴纳 1,000 美元罚款，你就可以走了。
I am a practicing physician.
我是一名执业医师。
Su Wei'an?
Su Wei'an?
Su Weian, a student in the clinical medicine class of 2012.
苏伟安， 2012级临床医学班学生。
gentlemen. Gu,
先生。顾,
You still remember me.
你还记得我。
I haven't seen many students who are absent from exams
我没见过很多 缺考的学生
Because of saving people.
因为救人。
Your name made a deep impression on me then.
那时你的名字给我留下了深刻的印象。
Su Wei'an,
Su Wei'an,
I thought you would make an excellent doctor
我以为你会成为 一名出色的医生
But I didn't expect you to drop out of school.
但我没想到你会退学。
Why did you drop out of school?
你为什么退学？
Studying medicine is too difficult and there is no money.
学医太难了， 又没钱，
So I gave up.
所以我放弃了。
Pay the fine quickly
赶紧交罚款吧
Can you give me a discount?
你能给我折扣吗？
Fifty percent off?
百分之五十折扣？
Five hundred dollars?
五百美元？
OK?
好的？
Are you bargaining?
你们在讨价还价吗？
That doesn't work, right?
那行不通，对吧？
Five hundred dollars?
五百美元？
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Where is my money?
我的钱在哪里？
Oh no, I don't have enough cash either.
哦不，我也没有足够的现金。
PhD. Gu,
博士。顾,
You must have money.
你必须有钱。
Please help her.
请帮助她。
Thank you, Dr. Gu.
谢谢你，顾博士。
Thank you, my teacher Teacher Gu.
谢谢您，我的老师顾老师。
don't thank me
别谢我
Or call me your teacher.
或者叫我你的老师。
my students
我的学生们
Never give up halfway.
绝不半途而废。
Su Wei'an,
Su Wei'an,
If I find out you provide treatment
如果我发现你提供治疗
Again without permission,
再次未经许可，
I will cooperate with the police to bring you to justice.
我会配合警方 将你绳之以法。
Remember this.
记住这一点。
Doctor Gu, we will pay you back.
顾医生，我们会还你的。
Hello Hong.
你好，洪。
Hello Mr. Zhou.
周先生您好。
Hey guy,
嘿伙计，
Do you still have Maotai in your store?
你店里还有茅台吗？
Those bottles of Moutai I ordered for you last month,
上个月我给你订的那几瓶茅台酒，
Can I buy it back?
我可以买回来吗？
Have you finished all three boxes?
你把三盒都喝完了吗？
Just one bottle?
只有一瓶吗？
Two bottles? OK!
两瓶？好的！
Forged..
伪造的..
No fakes. I don't sell fakes.
没有假货。我不卖假货。
The general is an expert on China. You know.
将军是中国问题专家。 你懂的。
If he had tasted it, he would know.
如果他尝过，他就会知道。
Give me a quote.
给我一个报价。
This (product quality) is really deceiving!
这（商品质量）真是骗人！
What a hassle to buy some wine!
买点酒多麻烦啊！
Su Wei'an,
Su Wei'an,
Do you still consider me your friend?
你还把我当作你的朋友吗？
I flew halfway around the world
我飞越了半个地球
I came to see you today,
今天来看你，
I've been running all day for you
为了你奔波了一整天
I still use my acting skills to cry for you
还用演技 为你哭
- But you won't look into my eyes? - My fault.
- 但你却不肯看我的眼睛吗？ - 我的错。
My fault.
我的错。
Come on, come on, have some shrimp.
来来来，吃点虾吧。
Your favorite shrimp.
你最喜欢的虾。
Don't do that.
不要那么做。
to be honest. How is this going?
说实话。这是怎么回事？
only...
只是...
I lost General Kouyat's wine
我失去了库亚特将军的酒
- Now I... - Stop.
- 现在我... - 停下来。
Did I ask you about this?
我有问过你这件事吗？
I'm talking about Gu Yunzheng.
我说的是顾云铮。
Dr. Gu, your teacher Mr. Gu.
顾博士，你的老师顾先生。
Vomit.
吐吧。
Do you have feelings for him?
你对他有感觉吗？
That's enough, Jiang Muying.
够了，江暮影。
I'm in big trouble now.
我现在遇到了大麻烦。
How could I have thought of this?
我怎么能想到这个呢？
If the general is angry
如果将军生气了
Things will get out of control.
事情将会失控。
beautiful.
美好的。
I won't ask you about Dr. Gu again.
我不会再问你关于顾医生的事情了。
Let's talk about you.
让咱们聊聊你的事。
What's wrong with me?
我怎么了？
Stop pretending!
你别装了！
you are in lakaya
你在拉卡亚
But why did you lie to us about Paris?
但你为什么在巴黎的事上对我们撒谎呢？
return,
还，
When did you drop out of school?
你什么时候退学的？
Why?
为什么？
Didn't I make it clear?
我没有说清楚吗
At the police station?
在警察局？
It’s hard work and not profitable, right?
很辛苦，又不赚钱，对吧？
Yes.
是的。
Only Gu Yunzheng would believe it.
只有顾云峥才会相信。
Don't lie to me!
你别骗我！
You've wanted to be a doctor since you were a kid.
你从小就想成为一名医生。
now you tell me
现在你告诉我
Do you think you have no money to buy medicine?
你以为买药没钱
So you want to give up.
所以你想放弃。
Su Wei'an, do you think I really believe it?
苏危安，你觉得我真的会相信吗？
And you, Su Wei'an,
And you, Su Wei'an,
I have never been the kind of person who loves money.
从来就不是那种 爱钱的人。
I do love money,
我确实爱钱，
Very.
非常。
You came all the way to Lakaya
你千里迢迢来到了拉卡亚
Make dangerous money and risk your life.
赚取危险的金钱 ，冒着生命危险。
Is it because of what happened to your thesis that year?
是因为 你当年的论文发生了什么事情吗？
of course not.
当然不是。
Or is it because of your father's accident?
还是因为你父亲的意外？
River,
江，
People will change.
人们会改变。
I just want to make money now.
我现在只想赚钱。
I want to enjoy life.
我想享受生活。
I don't want to suffer every day in that medical school
我不想 在那所医学院每天受苦
And working hard but not making much money.
并且努力工作 却赚不了多少钱。
you should not
你不必
It’s such a hard struggle here. All right?
在这里奋斗得那么辛苦。好吧？
Come back to China with me.
跟我一起回中国吧。
Jiang, I know
蒋，我知道
You care about me.
你很关心我。
but
但
I need a lot of money now
我现在需要很多钱
The more the better.
越多越好。
Okay, I'll make money with you.
好吧，我陪你一起赚钱。
I have liked following you since I was a child .
从小 我就喜欢跟着你。
This time is no exception.
这次也不例外。
I bought a one-way ticket.
我买了一张单程票。
Either you go back with me
要么你跟我回去
Or I can stay here with you.
或者我留在这儿陪你。
I won't leave without you.
没有你我不会离开。
Won't you take me away?
你不带我走吗？
Are you kidding me?
你在开玩笑吧？
Can your company give you such a long vacation?
你们公司能给 你这么长的假期吗？
Excellent,
出色地，
I resigned.
我辞职了。
again?
再次？
OMG.
我的天啊。
Our family’s real estate income
我们家的房产收入
Just renting money allows me to make money easily and effortlessly.
仅靠租金就可以让我 毫不费力地轻松赚钱。
Why endure the humiliation for a salary?
为何要为了工资而忍受屈辱
Only a few thousand?
只有几千个？
I don't want that,
我不想那样，
So I quit.
所以我退出了。
In two days?
在两天？
That won't work.
那不行。
If I don't get it today, I'm dead.
如果我今天不明白， 我就死定了。
So what happened to Wei An?
那么维安怎么了？
Is there enough Maotai for the general?
给将军准备的茅台酒够吗？
You only got so many bottles for your hard work tonight.
今晚辛苦你只得到了这么多瓶。
Have you asked the airport duty-free shop?
你问过机场免税店吗？
We can have people come in and buy it.
我们可以让人进去买。
It's not that easy.
它不是那么容易。
He is an expert on China.
他是中国问题专家。
All goods in duty-free shops are exported.
免税店里的 都是出口货。
What he wanted was the original Moutai.
他想要的是原版茅台酒。
what can we do?
我们可以做什么？
Here we are.
我们在这儿。
Who is that?
那是谁？
I have no idea. I dare not answer.
我不知道。我不敢回答。
They were calling me all night.
他们整个晚上都在给我打电话。
River,
江，
Why don't you buy a ticket and go back?
你为什么不买张票 然后回去呢？
I don't want you to get involved.
我不想让你卷入其中。
The general's people are terrible.
将军的人太可怕了。
I just got here. I will not leave.
我刚到这里。我不会离开。
Go away. get lost!
走开。迷路！
What's wrong?
怎么了？
hurry!
匆忙！
No.
不。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Go away!
走开!
Go there now!
现在就去那里吧！
who are they?
他们是谁？
General's people.
将军的人。
Go there now!
现在就去那里吧！
There is a box here.
这里有一个盒子。
A lot of people!
很多人！
There is only one carton.
只有一纸箱。
you! Carry this cardboard box into the car.
你！把这个纸箱搬上车。
Get that woman.
抓住那个女人。
Hide yourself.
隐藏自己。
Break the door open!
把门砸开！
No!
不！
All my money is in it.
我所有的钱都在里面。
Is your money more important than your life?
你的钱比你的生命还重要吗？
where are you going?
你要去哪里？
My snacks and hot sauce!
我的零食和辣椒酱！
seriously? chili sauce?
严重地？辣椒酱？
Your mother asked me to bring it to you.
你妈妈让我把它带给你。
you,
你，
Stand there.
站在那里。
Yes.
是的。
Notify all locations
通知所有地点
If Su Weian is found, report it to the general immediately.
如果发现苏伟安， 立即报告将军。
move!
移动！
let's go.
我们走吧。
my money! My shop!
我的钱！我的店哦！
This is too terrible!
这也太可怕了吧！
River,
江，
We can't go back today.
今天我们就回不去了。
The general's people just said
将军的人刚刚说
Said I ruined his party today
说我今天搞砸了他的宴会
They will catch me.
他们会抓住我。
why his people
为什么他的人
Acting like a gangster?
像流氓一样行事？
We can only pay him back.
我们只能还他钱了。
How could they smash and rob your home?
他们怎么能打砸抢你的家呢？
I'll call the police.
我会叫警察。
What can the police do?
警察能做什么？
He is like an emperor here
他在这里就像一个皇帝
Don't be afraid of anyone.
不害怕任何人。
where are we going
我们要去哪里
Staying the night tonight?
今晚过夜吗？
We can only find a hotel.
我们只能找个旅馆。
The general has ordered
将军已下令
There was no facility to accommodate me.
没有任何设施可以容纳我。
They grab me as soon as they see me.
他们一看到我就会抓住我。
Where can we go?
我们可以去哪里？
Hello!
你好！
Are you here to apply for a job as an interpreter?
您是来 申请口译员工作的吗？
I know a safe place to go.
我知道一个安全的地方可以去。
you do? This is your first day here.
你做？这是你来这里的第一天。
let's go.
我们走吧。
Come with me.
跟我来吧。
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
what are you waiting for? let's go.
你在等什么？我们走吧。
I'd better go back and apologize to the general.
我还是回去 向将军赔罪吧。
He won't really kill me.
他不会真的要我的命。
No.
不。
You are not even afraid of the general.
你连将军都不怕。
Are you afraid of coming to the hospital?
你害怕来医院吗？
Your store is destroyed and your business is gone.
你的店铺被毁了 ，你的生意也就没了。
This is your safest and best place.
这是您最安全、最好的地方。
Aren't you just here to make money?
你现在不就是为了赚钱吗？
They pay you every week
他们每周付钱给你
And the pay is good.
而且薪水不错。
what might be better for you
什么可能对你更好
Than this French translator works?
比这个法语翻译工作？
never.
决不。
♪Move the hands of the clock at night♪
♪夜晚移动时钟的指针♪
♪Noise replaced silence♪
♪喧闹取代了寂静♪
♪We act out the script of an encounter♪
♪我们演绎一场邂逅的剧本♪
♪The rainbow is embedded in the night♪
♪彩虹镶嵌在夜色中♪
♪And the wind blowing across the desert♪
♪还有吹过沙漠的风♪
♪Everyone has been our witness♪
♪都曾经是我们的见证者♪
♪Who doesn’t get lost in the vastness♪
♪谁不迷失在茫茫茫茫之中♪
♪Looking for a glimmer of hope? ♪
♪寻找一线生机？♪
♪Trapped in this city called destiny♪
♪被困在这座名为命运的城市♪
♪Still chasing stars♪
♪仍然追星♪
♪Don't worry, my lost loved ones♪
♪别担心，我失去的亲人♪
♪Your lonely soul is warmed by wine♪
♪你孤独的灵魂因酒而温暖♪
♪Let me hug your wounds♪
♪让我拥抱你的伤口♪
♪You shine like a star♪
♪你像星星一样闪耀♪
♪Flickers in the loneliest moments♪
♪在最孤独的时候闪烁♪
♪Move the hands of the clock at night♪
♪夜晚移动时钟的指针♪
♪Noise replaced silence♪
♪喧闹取代了寂静♪
♪We act out the script of an encounter♪
♪我们演绎一场邂逅的剧本♪
♪The rainbow is embedded in the night♪
♪彩虹镶嵌在夜色中♪
♪And the wind blowing across the desert♪
♪还有吹过沙漠的风♪
♪Everyone has been our witness♪
♪都曾经是我们的见证者♪
♪Who doesn’t get lost in the vastness♪
♪谁不迷失在茫茫茫茫之中♪
♪Looking for a glimmer of hope? ♪
♪寻找一线生机？♪
♪Trapped in this city called destiny♪
♪被困在这座名为命运的城市♪
♪Still chasing stars♪
♪仍然追星♪
♪Don't worry, my lost loved ones♪
♪别担心，我失去的亲人♪
♪Your lonely soul is warmed by wine♪
♪你孤独的灵魂因酒而温暖♪
♪Let me hug your wounds♪
♪让我拥抱你的伤口♪
♪You shine like a star♪
♪你像星星一样闪耀♪
♪Flickers in the loneliest moments♪
♪在最孤独的时候闪烁♪